what would you say
is the most important thing for the
beginning of practice
i guess the intention that you want to
practice
like the clearer that intention is the
clearer your reasons for
for practice are the the better
likelihood you know successful effort there will be
so like you really want to know
why you want to practice why you're
doing this
and if you're not clear or if you're
well because of this because of that
well you make sure you're clarified
because lack of clarity on that level initially
lack of clarity on that level initially
can result in later on
in lacking the effort lacking
determination to make the effort
so that's why like again you need you
would take it seriously
if you recognize the necessity of
practice and the right reasons behind it like oh
and the right reasons behind it like oh
this is not really
optional it's just i have a limited time
to address the existence
in me being subject to suffering and who
knows when i will have another
opportunity for that
so you take it serious from that point
of view
and if you keep that then the effort
will be there generated from that very
clarity of that intention so knowing
what what you want basically what is your
what you want basically what is your
goal for this practice yeah
yes
setting the goal actually yeah it just
makes me feel good
so is that my goal to feel good
what is my goal to be free from
suffering that is my goal so the
practice should lead me there that's same with
should lead me there that's same with
the buddha did who can teach the way out
and he followed these different teachers
they didn't meet the goal and he moved
on
he did not compromise on the goal as a
result of it
and that's important because sometimes
people would yes i wanted to be free
from suffering
the teacher said well don't worry about
it there is nothing to be attained
so i'm kind of fine with it and
basically you abandon your own goals
that you started with
but you don't have to and you shouldn't
especially if you read the suttas you
realize no no there are things to be
attained goals to be reached that's why the
goals to be reached that's why the
buddha outlined them
as a measure as a kind of almost like an
inspiration an incentive for people to
go for that
and the clearer you are about what those
goals are
the easier it will be to to get a clear
picture and make the effort towards him
that's often he said in sutra because he
listens to the wise man
he understands what he's saying then he
understands what needs to be done so he
measures the task
oh this is the goal of practice so he
measures his task of how to achieve that
and he sets to do it because he's clear
now as to what the task is
so ask yourself as somebody who wants to
just start to practice
or has been practicing do i know what
the actual practice is
that does result in uprooting of
underlying tendencies of
lust aversion delusion and freeing me
from suffering am i clear can i explain
it to somebody else how to practice
with guaranteed results or am i still
just sort of you know
stabbing in the dark sometimes i feel
good sometimes i don't but i hope for
the best
and you will stay in that state of
ambiguity without any goals achieved that matter
without any goals achieved that matter
because you're not making effort to
clarify them
no no what is my goal what is the go
what does suit is talk about what should
i strive for what should i do
what is the gradual training that i must
accomplish myself in let me do
that understand it measure the extent of
effort and then make the app
and that's the only way that the dhamma
can be known
of course through that
individual effort of discerning things
absolutely correct
absolutely making things clear to
yourself and
exactly there is no method there is no
instruction that somebody can just tell
you and you go through it mechanically
they will result in that
you need to do that and see that for
yourself it's up to you
to basically start start applying
the instructions you did come across and
see if they bare results
if not either upgrade your effort or
upgrade instructions
but the results must follow
the buddha said it himself so if if
there are no visible results
visible like
milestones of your freedom from
suffering you should really re-evaluate
because if you're doing things rightly
the results will have to happen even if
you don't want them
if you're doing things rightly results
should occur you